Okay, after having praised polymorphism so much
in the last video, I want to post
another short video to provide a
warning in particular about an interaction
that polymorphism can have with testing.
So, there will be a short session
in an interpreter session here,
where I want to point out something which may,
at first, be a bit surprising or puzzling.
And then we will see what is going on.
And it has to do with
polymorphism as a warning, okay.
And so, let me actually call GHCi.
And let me not load some source file,
but simply the QuickCheck library,
so that I can write some quick tests.
Okay, and let's actually try to test our
polymorphic 'reverse' function that I have
introduced in or discussed in the previous video.
So, what could be a nice property
of the 'reverse' function?
So, for example, it certainly is
the case that if I take the length
of a reversed list, then that is the
same as the length of the list itself.
Right.
So, reversing a list doesn't
change the length of that list.
That seems a reasonable property.
So, let me check this, and it
says, yes, actually, that is true.
Okay.
And I could think of some further properties of
the 'reverse' function, also check them
and find: Well, they are all true.
Okay, then at some point, I might become
a bit overambitious, or maybe a bit crazy
and claim well, let me actually from the
property above, simply omit the 'length' call,
that would give the claim
that 'reverse' of xs is xs.
This is wrong, I would expect, right?
So, reversing a list is not the
same as simply having that list.
However, if I run this, it is accepted.
And that's not by happenstance by
somehow the random generator that
accidentally created 100 lists
where this is actually true.
No, it's not true.
That's not the case.
It is always successful.
Nevertheless, if I actually call the 'reverse'
function, it really doesn't have this property.
'Reverse' of "abc" is not "abc", it's "cba".
Yes.
And indeed, if I do this for many examples,
it always doesn't show the behavior that I
have successfully tested with QuickCheck.
So, what has happened?
Well, what I told you to do
in order to investigate what
is going on with QuickCheck
tests, either for your own
peace of mind to know what has actually
been tested or just out of curiosity.
And you can always replace quickCheck by verboseCheck,
and you will see what input was checked.
Apparently, it didn't check
"abc" or [1..10], because
then it wouldn't have made those
wrong claims that everything was okay.
Let's do a verbose check of the same property.
Ah, now, this looks interesting and strange.
What has happened?
Actually, the property has been tested 100
times, but on very strange lists on lists,
which always contain this trivial element.
And indeed, if I take a list like this, where
everything is the same, namely this strange
empty value here, then of course, reversing
this list is the same as the list itself.
Because if the list contains only one element
several times, but all elements are the same,
then of course, reversing
doesn't change the list.
Okay, so what is the lesson here?
If you check a polymorphic function,
like the 'reverse' function,
it's really important on what to check it.
Simply saying QuickCheck please, test this, then
QuickCheck could, and in this case it does, take
an element type for the lists
to check here, for example,
that is not strong enough to actually
show that our property was wrong.
Yes.
So, what happened that these strange
lists were tested, and they all are okay,
but this doesn't tell me anything about
the real function, not much at least.
At least it doesn't tell me that 'reverse'
is the identity, which it looks like.
Okay, so what can we do or what should we
do when we test a polymorphic function?
We should make sure what we test or what type
it is, you shouldn't leave this to QuickCheck,
because this can lead to these
artifacts or wrong results.
How can we say this?
Well, for example, you could say well,
let's check this on lists of integers.
And I can do this by in the property,
you're assigning or declaring that this xs should
be a list of integers, for example, right?
Then I prevent that QuickCheck makes a decision
and chooses this strange element and type here.
Okay, and if I do this, then actually,
QuickCheck finds out that the property does
not hold. Right here, very quickly, it finds
a counterexample, namely for the list [0,1].
It's not true that reversing
it gives the same list.
And I could also have done this with strings.
For example, I could say for
every String this will hold.
I would expect that QuickCheck finds a
counterexample. It says no, for a string "ab",
it's not true, the property, or I could
even have taken lists of Bools here,
it would have found a counterexample that
is [True, False] in the context of it.
So, for any non-trivial type, you get a counterexample,
except for the case, where we don't give a type,
where we simply leave it to QuickCheck
and QuickCheck makes a very poor choice,
namely, this one. Okay, so we have to be
very aware of this when we write tests.
And of course, in our tests for your
Autotool submissions, we take care of this.
But if you want to test on your own, and
you have a polymorphic function, you need to
invest a bit of thinking, what actually you
want to check your polymorphic function on.
In this case, we shouldn't check it on this
trivial type. Okay, it is not a defect per se,
in logic or anything like that, it's
some care that you have to use in order
to know what you're actually testing.
And if you're uncertain, you can
always use verboseCheck, and then
you see what has happened behind the scenes.